Guide to the Gerald K. Geerlings Prints 1975-1976 PR 390
New-York Historical Society
Gerald K. Geerlings prints
1975-1976
New-York Historical Society
Geerlings, Gerald K. (Gerald Kenneth), 1897-
PR 390
1.5 Linear feet in one flat file
Eleven prints of New York City scenes of the 1970s, drawn, printed and signed by Gerald K. Geerlings (1897-1998).
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically by year, and alphabetical by title within year.
Biographical / Historical
Printmaker, architect and author Gerald Kenneth Geerlings was born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin on 18 April 1897. After serving in the military during World War I, he studied in England at St. John's College, Cambridge University. The next year he enrolled at the School of Architecture, University of Pennsylvania. After graduation he worked as an architect for several firms before starting his own. His printmaking career began when he was working as an architect. By 1928 he traveled to London to study etching at the Royal College of Art. He won his first award for a print in 1931, awarded by the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts for "Jeweled City." In 1933 the Depression and a move to Connecticut caused him to interrupt his printmaking career. He returned to printmaking in the 1970s, producing a group of lithographs on Paris and New York City, including a series inspired by the American Bicentennial in 1976. Geerlings died in Connecticut at 101 years old in 1998.
(The above note was based on the biographical note found on the website of Kiechel Fine Art Gallery.)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jeannette Flamm Brockman, 2019.
Scope and Contents
Eleven prints of New York City scenes, drawn and printed by Gerald K. Geerlings (one print has two copies). All prints are signed in pencil by Geerlings.
The container list includes the title of all prints in the collection. The title shown is that noted in pencil by Geerlings on the print. The scope note beneath each title includes in quotation marks the more literal description of the scene depicted as included in the original print by Geerlings. Additional description of the scene that was added by the processing archivist is shown in the note outside of quotation marks.
Prints (visual works).; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.)
- Acropolis Americana, 1975 (Folder FF-1)
  Scope and Contents
  "Lincoln Center, New York"
- Aspirations Unlimited (2 prints), 1975 (Folder FF-1)
  "Nieuw Amsterdam, 1656 - New York, 1975". View of colonial New York, with modern lower Manhattan skyline behind in mist (with World Trade Center towers).
- Hail Utopia!, 1975 (Folder FF-1)
  "Central Park South, New York". Park interior with city buildings rising in the distance.
- Old Fort, New Fortresses, 1975 (Folder FF-1)
  "The Battery, New York" with a "Phantom Warship, circa 1730" in harbor at bottom right. Includes view of Fort Clinton, with lower Manhattan buildings behind.
- Sing Hallelujah!, 1975 (Folder FF-1)
  "Central Park, New York". Park interior with city buildings rising in the distance.
- Bicentennial Neighbors, 1976 (Folder FF-1)
  "Water and Broad Streets, Lower Manhattan"
- Bicentennial Oasis, 1976 (Folder FF-1)
  "Hanover Square, Lower Manhattan"
- Dawn of a New Era, 1976 (Folder FF-1)
  "Gen. Washington Bade Farewell to His Officers Here at Fraunces Tavern, Lower Manhattan, 4th December 1783"
- Midtown Oasis, 1976 (Folder FF-1)
  "Avenue of the Americas, North of West 49th Street, New York"
- Old Spire, New Towers, 1976 (Folder FF-1)
  "St. Paul's, Trinity Parish, Erected 1766. Broadway at Fulton Street, New York." World Trade Center towers rise behind St. Paul's.